<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short discourse concerning the work of God in this nation, and the duty of all good people, both governors and governed, in this their day.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3584</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E986_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207794</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866823</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866823</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119109</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93207)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119109)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 147:E986[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short discourse concerning the work of God in this nation, and the duty of all good people, both governors and governed, in this their day.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R.W. for Francis Tyton at the Sign of the three Daggers in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Goodness --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119109:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT DISCOURSE CONCERNING The WORK of GOD IN THIS NATION, AND The DUTY of all good People, BOTH Governors and Governed, IN This their DAY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton</hi> at the Sign of the three Daggers in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1659.</p>
            <p>
               <add>June. 25</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119109:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119109:2"/>
            <head>A ſhort diſcourſe concerning the work of God in this Nation, and the duty of all good people, both Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Governed, in this their day.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He various dealings of God with his people in theſe Nations, have all along, of late years, to ſome diſcerning ſpirits, appeared full of Fatherly love and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs. The Faith of theſe Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtaggered not at all, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the great ſtumbling-blocks which have by our back-ſliding, been caſt into the way of Gods work. I hope the Lord is now ariſing to make good their word; yea, and that the very ſnares wherein he hath permitted ſome honeſt perſons to be entangled, and the ſcourges with which he hath viſited us for our Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, will be made effectual means of recovering, ſtrengthening, and perfecting a teſtimony for Liberty, Righteouſneſs and Judgement upon the earth. For though ſome of them of underſtanding have fallen, yet this hath been but to try them, to purge and make them white, even to the time of the end, becauſe it is yet for an appointed time, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.35.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119109:3"/>
            <p>Certainly it was the admirable wiſdom of God, to ſuffer ſo many interruptions of his glorious work, as have for theſe laſt years ſprung up amongſt us. He only acted herein the part of a wiſe Maſter-builder, who for a time deſiſts from raiſing his intended Fabrick, till firſt he hath prepared all materials requiſite to the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying it on. Now if we impartially ſearch into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and imperfections of the whole body of good people, which formerly rendred them unfit to proceed in the work of Reformation, and obſtructed the eſtabliſhment of Freedom and Equity in the midſt of us, we ſhall then find good cauſe to acknowledge, That the Lord in great goodneſs and wiſdom (though alſo in judgement and diſpleaſure) let ſome of us run back to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Egypt</hi> into the Wilderneſs, and chaſtened others by the ſtrokes of their own Brethren and familiar friends; that thus he might ſhew us what was in our hearts, and what folly and falſhood is wrapt up in the minds of his children, even of the beſt of his children, which requires the rod of correction to drive it out. And if it ſhall pleaſe the great God of Heaven, the ſearcher of all hearts, now at laſt to ſanctifie unto us his chaſtiſements and our ſtumblings, we ſhall enjoy a ſweet and precious fruit of all. For by what hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen us theſe laſt times, we are well cautioned how to ſteer our future courſe, both in publick and perſonal exigencies, off from thoſe dangerous Rocks which we our ſelves or others in our obſervation have ſplit upon, to the prophanation of Gods Temple, and the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of their own good name and conſcience.</p>
            <p>The intent therefore of this ſhort paper is to diſcuſs a little the grounds, why we ſtayed ſo long in the birth, why God hitherto hath ſo long diſappointed our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, and made ſuch delay in ſatisfying our hunger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119109:3"/>deſires after Liberty and Righteouſneſs in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Frame of theſe Nations: and withall to awaken all good Perſons, Parliament, Army, and all that love the righteous Old Cauſe, to meet the Lord in the preſent Overtures which his Providence makes to us with meek and broken hearts, fitted to become the ſubjects of that bleſſed and ſaving work which God hath yet to work out among us.</p>
            <p>Only give me leave firſt to conſider with you a while how throughly the tender mercies of God do allure us to the performance of our duty before expreſt. No peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the whole earth have had amongſt them more evident footſteps of divine Wiſdom, Power and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, then this ſinful Nation; eſpecially thoſe in it who have been honeſt and faithful, whoſe hearts and eyes were ready to fail for the ſalvation of God. Their own ſouls could not have wiſht or expected a more ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable revival of Gods work, nor a more explicit and publique approbation to the Ancient good Cauſe, then God himſelf hath been pleaſed to give in the eyes of our own people, and of all Nations, in calling this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to the exerciſe of their juſt authority after ſo long an interruption.</p>
            <p>As for the ſeaſonableneſs of this notable turn, the low ebb whereunto the Nation is reduced by male executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Government (to the exhauſting of the publique Treaſuries, and contracting of debts, to the deadning of Trade both Forraign and Domeſtick, and giving all our Enemies abroad and within our bowels, advantages againſt us) doth ſufficiently diſcover that nothing could befall us more agreeable, nor more in ſeaſon; though indeed of this the Parliament it ſelf muſt be left to give more full evidence by their future counſels and actions: yet the good condition in which things
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119109:4"/>ſtood, when by an uſurped force the Parliament was interrupted, comparatively unto what they have ſince declined into, may juſtly quicken our hopes, of being again, through Gods bleſſing, recovered into as good, yea a much better condition then ever. For what hath God deſigned by permitting ſuch diſorderly and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous endeavours of men towards Tyranny and ſelf-exaltation, and that of men obliged to the contrary by all the Obligations that Vows and Conviction could lay upon them, as of late years he hath, unleſs to ſhew us all in their examples, what we are, how frail and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveable in all the zeal and goodly appearance of our own righteouſneſs; and to ſhew us alſo how inconſiſtent a private ſelfiſh mind is with righteous rule; which truths once throughly learnt and experienced by our Governours, will admirably fit them for a right diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of thoſe weighty truſts which are committed to them.</p>
            <p>This late remarkable paſſage of Gods Providence in reſtoring the Parliament of this Common-wealth to the Throne, hath not only been ſeaſonable, but likewiſe a very expreſs and open an Ownal of the Good Cauſe formerly engaged for, and that greatly to the honor of them the Grand Engagers therein; as alſo of them in the Army, whoſe hearts the Lord moved to earneſtly requeſt and make way for their Seſſion. God himſelf hath honoured you in the ſight of all people, and made your cup run over in the preſence of your Enemies; God ſeems willing, that you above others, you who have already heretofore through his bleſſing, made good progreſs in his reforming work, ſhould now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed towards the accompliſhing thereof. Some of you he hath refined in the furnace of ſufferings. Others of your Number, troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he hath cut off with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119109:4"/>the ſtroke of his hand; &amp; ſome whom he ſuffer'd to fall back with the torrent of the times, he hath ſince toucht, I hope, with a deep and godly ſenſe of their fallings: and all this to try and to humble you, that he may do you good in the end. The Lord hath been hewing and poliſhing you for ſome more noble uſe then ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you were prepared for, and hath now with a high hand, and an out-ſtretched arm gathered you together to put you yet again upon the proof, whither you will be a willing and obedient people in the day of his power. It greatly therefore concerns you and all the good people, diligently to ſearch out what the holy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and perfect will of God is, which by all his various diſpenſations he would diſcover to us, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline our hearts to the obedience of; what the reaſons of his carrying us back from the borders of liberty and reſt, which once before we were entring into, under the conduct of this Parliament, into a Wilderneſs of confuſion, ſufferings and oppreſſions during the late uſurpation; and what his deſigns in thus mercifully rallying us, in order, if we be not rebellious, to our more compleat entrance into the Land of Reſt and Truth, and fuller conqueſt over all the <hi>Canaanites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The main thing in which all Gods people, generally from the higheſt to the loweſt, have been too unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, is denying of ſelf, (not corrupt ſinful ſelf only, but righteous and holy ſelf) and contemning thoſe allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of gain, which puft up the mind of man with boaſting and vainglory. This ſurely is that which we are call'd to be more fully inſtructed in; and in the firſt place thoſe that are Rulers. The Changes and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnings we have had in this corner of the world, do loudly proclaim to us, that which the Rock of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaid to <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.3. <hi>He that ruleth over men
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119109:5"/>muſt he juſt, ruling m the fear of the Lord;</hi> that is, he muſt receive the Pattern for his Rule, and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to it from Jeſus Chriſt, the Fountain of all juſt Government, and not ſeek them in himſelf, in his own ſingle intereſt or glory. A ſelf-glorying and ſelf-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching spirit is perfectly oppoſite to the Kingdom of Chriſt, and to the common advantage of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Our Lord himſelf (though ſo ſpotleſs and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as he was) ſaith, <hi>I ſeek not mine own glory. If I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour my ſelf, my honour is nothing. I ſpeak not of my ſelf;</hi> and again, <hi>Not my will be done:</hi> by all which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and others ſuch like, we ſee plainly, that Chriſt having, conſideration of himſelf as ſingle and alone in his righteous Manhood, utterly refuſes to ſpeak or act in that capacity. <hi>I do</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>nothing of my ſelf, but as my Father hath taught me, I ſpeak theſe things; he that ſent me is with me; the Father hath not left me alone; For I do always thoſe things that pleaſe him;</hi> Look how Chriſt in this reſpect deports him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the exerciſe of his rule towards his Head, the Father, (ſo ought you moſt Renowned Patriots, in Parliament and Army) to demean your ſelves, in the exerciſe of your Rule, towards Chriſt, who is your Head; you ought to ſee an inſufficiency in the wiſdom and ſtrength of fleſh, a weakneſs in your ſelves left alone, even in your beſt eſtate; and that your ſafety and force lies in being yoaked to Chriſt through meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſpirit and ſubmiſſion of will to him in all your enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>Although Popular Government in a Free State, conſidered in it ſelf, may juſtly of all others be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted here with us the moſt natural and adequate <hi>medium,</hi> whereby to attain and ſecure the peoples Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and welfare, (which is one great end of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119109:5"/>yet if the perſons managing this Government, be ſlaves to their ambitious luſts, and ſervants to gain, the Government will be difficultly preſerved from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting. Good rules indeed in its conſtitution (as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent change of office and reſidence, and the balan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing particular mens intereſts, and ſetting bounds to their riches and greatneſs, with the like) may greatly avail to its preſervation, and are needful. But we ſhall never be ſettled upon the right Baſis of good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, till Chriſt reveal himſelf in our Rulers, as the Corner-ſtone of the whole building, teaching them to deny themſelves, and naturally to take care of the Common-weal, by faithfully and impartially diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting to every man his portion of Freedom, Juſtice and Encouragement in due ſeaſon, and doing right to all without reſpect of perſons; not ſiding with part of the good people in neglect of the reſt, nor engroſſing to themſelves the benefits of power and rule, to the unjuſt excluſion or oppreſſion of any; the diſcovery of this juſt upright ſpirit in our Magistracy, will terrifie their enemies, make glad all honeſt hearts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the diſ-affected of the excellency of the Good Cauſe ſo long conteſted for.</p>
            <p>The wiſe King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> tells us, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.9. there is a time when one man rules over another to his own hurt. And when is that, but at ſuch time as he rules in a ſelf-promoting and ſelf-ſecuring way, contrary to Gods heart, and to the common right: for this corrupts his ſpirit, miſ-leading him from the fear of God, and ſets him at defiance with the popular Intereſt; ſo that he is expoſed to their ſevere judgement, when they ſhall recover power and liberty; as alſo to the wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſpleaſure of God, whoſe powerful arm executes his righteous will everywhere, and upon all perſons
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119109:6"/>without controle or limitation; that therefore which next follows in the ſame Chapter is conſiderable; And <hi>ſo I ſaw the wicked buried, who had come and gone from the place of the Holy, and they were forgotten in the City where they had ſo done;</hi> this is alſo vanity which we have ſeen too in part fulfilled upon ſome great men of this laſt age of the world, that a long time went together with the upright to the Houſe of God, and had a mighty name in the viſible Church, the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> below: But in the generation to come their name ſhall be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out, and the memory of them be cut off from the earth, becauſe they were enemies to the Crucifying work of Saving-grace.</p>
            <p>It is obſervable, that God hath ſuffered ſome bitter degenerate root or other to grow up &amp; ſhew it ſelf in ſo many viſible forms of Worſhip, and ſects of Religious Profeſſors ſucceſſively, from Popery to Epiſcopacy, and ſo downward even to theſe very times: when they have once come to greatneſs, and increaſed into a Kingdom, what envy, pride, ſelf-confidence, bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt diſſenting Brethren, and other ſuch fruits of a private ſelf-magnifying ſpirit, have ſuddainly ſprung forth and obtained deep rooting in the midſt of them! It is worth obſervation alſo on the other hand, that ſome gleanings may be found in various and differing forms and ſects of perſons, who we cannot but in our conſciences judge and hope are accepted with God, and faithful in the main: From hence certainly the Lord would inſtruct us how empty a thing the form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is without the power of it, and that the power of Godlineſe does nevertheleſs well conſiſt with divers forms. Circumciſion is nothing, nor uncircumciſion, but the new creature; and the peace of God is upon all thoſe that walk according to this rule. But, alas how?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119109:6"/>how greatly do we yet deviate from it, whileſt every one is apt to meaſure his Brother from his harmony or diſſent in opinion and worldly intereſt, rather then from the new Birth, and a meek Godly converſation? Such as worſhip God in Spirit, rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, and have no confidence in fleſh, ſuch are the true circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion: they have the end of the Law, and of all Gods Ordinances and Inſtitutions fulfilled in them. Nor doth this conſideration ſlightly concern our Magiſtrates. Every ſort almoſt of profeſſours is eagerly deſirous of your countenance, and too many endeavour to mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polize it to themſelves; nor only ſo, but they would engage your Authority in ſuppreſſing whatſoever is contrary to their way. But I truſt the Lord will fully open your eyes to ſee the falſhood and deceipt of this ſpirit, which is ſo much the more dangerous, as the form wherein 'tis enthroned is more glorious then others, or the people in whom it rules more zealous, and in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance holy.</p>
            <p>There is but two ſorts of Religion in the general, of thoſe who call themſelves Chriſtian. The one hath its center in ſelf or nature, (I mean not degenerate and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted nature, as in the Fall; for nothing can dwell there except irreligion, but) renewed through the common light and grace of God, to its primitive luſtre and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (in kinde, though not in meaſure) wherein man was firſt created. This ſort of Religious perſons are clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the common pollutions of the world through luſt, by the knowledge of Chriſt. They are a knowing enlightened people, forward in ſerving God, and ſtrict in the obedience of his Ordinances, according to their interpretation of them. But their fear of God is taught them by the precepts of man, tis derived to them in a humane natural ſpirit and light. Self is indeed the ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119109:7"/>ſcope of theſe mens Religion: And therefore they delight to diſtinguiſh themſelves by ſomewhat in the formal part or outward circumſtances of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that may ſerve to embody them in a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding between themſelves, and an open diſtinction from other; and then from their own intereſt, as thus a ſimple diſtinct body, make judgement of all diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parties, favouring or diſ-affecting them, as they do or do not conform to their model and opinions. This kind of Religion wherever it is, will unavoidably har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour a perſecuting ſpirit, which is the brand of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; ſelf-love is the very ſoul of this Religion. Thoſe that are of it, can follow God ſo far as ſome gain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crues to their fleſhly mind by his ſervice, but no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; they would have ſomewhat whereof to glory in the ſight of God and before men, and would not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in God himſelf only; proſperity detects their filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and deſtroyes their ſouls. Affliction ſhakes them off like untimely fruit, but they muſt and will grow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Wheat, until the Lord root them up, and conſume them at his coming.</p>
            <p>The ſecond kind of Religion hath its foundation and center in the love of God, and unity of Spirit with Chriſt who is the Head of the Church. Such as are of this Religion, love Chriſt for himſelf, and all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers for the love of him. They judge of the members by their proportion and Symmetry with their Head; not by comparing others to themſelves. They would have none follow them further then they follow Chriſt. Nor do they comply with any implicitly, having mens perſons in admiration for advantage, but receive and cheriſh the truth wherever they meet it, for the love of it ſelf. They fight againſt errour with ſpiritual weapons; and their faith ſtands not in the wiſdom nor
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119109:7"/>ſtrength of man, but in the power and free grace of God. The Kingdom of God in which they are, is not in meat and drink; but righteouſneſs, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt. He that in theſe things ſerves Chriſt, is acceptable to God, and approved of them; ſo far as bodily exerciſe may profit themſelves or their Brother in the beſt things, they are willing to uſe it, but Godlineſs is the thing they chiefly intend, which hath the promiſes of this life, and of the life to come. The variety of forms cannot ſo diſguiſe the true Saint, as to deter theſe from acknowledging him; nor ſo beautifie the natural man or carnal profeſſor, as to induce theſe to magnifie and exalt him. Fulneſs cannot utterly ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enate their hearts from God; ſufferings can never ſeparate them from the love of Chriſt, or a faithful pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in well-doing. Gods out-goings in the midſt of us, have clearly diſcovered this diſtinction in Religion; he now expects, that the former of them, which is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the letter and form only, ſhould not ſuffice us, and the latter which is inward in the power and ſpirit, ſhould take place in us.</p>
            <p>I know no greater ſign of Chriſts haſtning to ſet up his righteous Rule openly in the world, then the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodying of all his Saints in a free fellowſhip with, and hearty owning of one another in the ſubſtance of true Religion, which is to do juſtly, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with God. For when <hi>Zion,</hi> the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Lord, his holy City, ſhall once be raiſed out of the duſt, her King will ſoon ſhew himſelf in the midſt of her, in the apparent exerciſe of his glorious Dominion upon the earth: Now the conſtitution of this Holy City the New Jeruſalem is ſuch as is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. at the end.</p>
            <p>Firſt it is comprehenſive of all Saints, ſo as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119109:8"/>and gather into the Unity of the Spirit, all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and righteous ones every where, whom God acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges to be his Beloved Seed, though their meaſures be divers, their haltings and blemiſhes great. <hi>The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions if them that are ſaved ſhall walk in the light of the glory of God and the Lamb which lightens this City. And the Rings of the Earth do bring their glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour into it. And the Gates of it ſhall not be ſhut at all by day; for there ſhall be no night there: and they ſhall bring the glory and honour of the Nations into it.</hi> All the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light muſt have free admittance into this New Jeruſalem; they are by the New birth made free of this City. None may upon any pretence, deny them free commerce in it: Thoſe Societies therefore, that have not this largeneſs of heart, to receive into the bonds of Brotherhood all the members of Chriſt, (from the moſt honourable to the moſt abject and the out-caſt) are not to be thought the Heavenly Zion, or Holy City of God, wherein God ſhall tabernacle with men, as is promiſed, in order to ſubject the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the world to his Scepter. 'Tis true, ſuch Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties may have many in them that are precious to God, and actually Saints, but they lie yet among the pots, ſcattered abroad in the rubbiſh of <hi>Babel:</hi> they are not framed together, and built up in the viſible frame and conſtitution proper to Zion. This Holy City when ſhe ſhall once manifeſtly appear in her beauty, will ſend forth a collective influence, able to attract and knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the hearts of all Gods dear children, out of every tongue, Nation, Language and people.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This New Jeruſalem from above, hath alſo in its conſtitution an excluſive power, by which all the wicked and hypocritical are kept out of her, verſ. 27. <hi>And there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119109:8"/>that defileth, neither whatſoever worketh abomination, or maketh a lie: but they which are written in the Lambs Book of Life.</hi> That very light and glory of Zion, which unites and gathers into one profeſt Body her own children, ſhall be as a thick cloud and gloomy darkneſs to all her enemies: And this by reaſon of the oppoſition between Zions conſtitution, (which is publique, large and capacious for the receipt and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of all the meek ſubjects of her King) and the conſtitution of the worldly Church, which is private, and reſtrained within the compaſs of ſelf glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying principles.</p>
            <p>The Lord I hope hath begun this great work of uniting his Saints, and embodying them, to the view of all, in the Spirit of holineſs, and in that love which is the Bond of perfectneſs: the ſpeedy progreſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of all the godly ought to endeavour. As the defection of the Churches from their Primitive ſimplicity, came through their cleaving to the perſons, opinions, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry or Intereſts of men (though good men) ſaying every one, <hi>I am of Paul, I am of Apollo, and I of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas, and I of Chriſt:</hi> ſo their return to the ſame ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity will be by ceaſing to glory in men, and cleaving entirely to their Head Chriſt Jeſus. In ſo doing they ſhall have a ſanctified uſe of all things. All is theirs, they are Chriſts, Chriſt is Gods.</p>
            <p>Happy are we, if after all the ſhaking work that God hath wrought in theſe Nations, we can be brought to ſit looſer from whatſoever may be ſhaken and removed, that ſo an entrance may be given us into the Kingdom of Chriſt that cannot be moved. But if upon the proof which the Lord is now bringing the good people of the Nation to, they ſtart aſide from him, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt through proſperity and power; if they apply not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119109:9"/>themſelves, with ſelf denyal and ſingleneſs of heart, to the advancement of liberty, common good, the power of godlineſs, and the unity of all Saints, we may well expect that God will yet proceed to ſhake us more terribly then ever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
